A Guide to the Ambrose Bierce Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #5992-j
Ambrose Bierce Collection 1896-1903
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
5992-j
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection (# 5992-j was purchased September 4, 1991.
Item Listing
- Letters
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C. to Harriet Hershberg, 1896 Apr 27; ALS, 3 p.
    [Bierce promises to have his photograph taken so that he can fulfill her request for his autograph and a photograph and playfully says, "When I get there [Oakland] I shall blindfold you, hypnotize you and command you to find my lost youth and freedom. Then I shall marry you alive and live happily ever after."]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C. to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1896 May 19; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Bierce writes "I am sending you by this mail the photograph of a bad old man with a scowl. The scowl, however, is not for you -you never saw it." He did not send a photograph to her big sister (Louise ?) because she already possessed one more pleasant looking]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Oakland, California to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, [1897 Jan 16]; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [He accepts all of her gratitude and regard for himself although he does not believe that he merits it. He regrets that he cannot say when he will be able to meet Mr. King but agrees to see him informally some time when he is in Oakland]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Los Gatos, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1897 Feb 23; ALS, 3 p. with envelope
    [In this letter, he sends Harriet some wild pansies growing by the wayside because they made him think of her, "I feel sure that the thought of you was put into my head by some divine intervention in the affairs of mortals, and for some purpose. My interpretation -with my feeble light and dull intuition-is that I am to send you some of those poor little frail pansies." He then goes on to explain that pansies are for thoughts and their old English name "hearts-ease" is better suited than "pansies = pensees"]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Los Gatos, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1897 Jul 11; ALS, 5 p., with envelope
    [Thanks her for sending him the ginger cakes which he tried to share with the horned-toads but they preferred grasshoppers. He declines to visit Oakland because his last visit cost him a month's illness but urges her to visit him in Los Gatos and to bring with her "that impossible paragon, the Pittsburgh sister -whom, however, I believe to be a myth."]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Los Gatos, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1897 Sep 19; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Asks Harriet for the Paris address of her "musical sweetheart," Will King, so that he can thank him for a book and asks her to write him concerning herself. Otherwise he will have to hire a detective to shadow her night and day and send him reports of everything he learns about her activities]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Los Gatos, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1898 Feb 11; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [He wishes to see her very badly but remembers all too well the last illness which he suffered in Oakland, promises to send tickets to Belle and her if they will visit him in Los Gatos for a Sunday afternoon, and mentions receiving a letter from her sister Louise]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Los Gatos, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Preston School, Waterman, California, 1898 Mar 7; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Expresses joy at the receipt of her letter for "it clears you of the solemn suspicion of running away from me in cold-blooded infraction of our understanding" but he also thinks "it very rascally of you to take all the sunshine out of Oakland to bestow it upon Iona"]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Los Gatos, California, to Harriet Hershberg, 1898 Apr 5; ALS, 3 p.
    [Sends another photograph to replace the damaged one along with several books to "the Colonel and the Major" and mentions a letter from Mamie who proved to be a charming traveling companion]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Los Gatos, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Waterman, California, 1898 May 1; ALS, 4 p., with envelope
    [Responding to her impression of his goodness Bierce writes, "It is pretty easy to be good to you, and I don't expect any credit for it in the books of the Recording Angel. He will say: `Bah ! who wouldn't be good to Hattie Hershberg?' and then he will debit me with one selfish motive." He also mentions Kodak photographs of a group consisting of Hattie, Mamie, Dave, Selma, Louise, and himself, while assuring her of his devotion, "you are still the only girl in the world; and if there is a man who does not love you he is a scoundrel." Referring to his experience in military life Bierce writes, "No, my pet scheme for making soldiers of the Major's little rascals is not practicable. The confounded Government is so particular about the moral character of its recruits that I couldn't enlist myself. This is a great disappointment to me. I had quite set my heart on getting Co. A into Cuba, to prove that bad boys make the best soldiers. But I'm assured that it cannot be done."]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1898 Jun 15; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Writes that he has severed all connections with Los Gatos and that his health is now good as he day dreams under the redwoods. He complains that thoughts of her often break in upon his reminiscences of the past, "Only the other day you want only interrupted the march of a column of troops from Readyville, Tennessee to Woodbury, Tennessee, which was not at all nice of you."]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1898 Jul 6; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Agrees to take her to see the soldiers and to expound every military mystery they encounter and to plan a trip to the country when she visits]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, [1898 Jul 18]; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Promises to visit San Francisco next Sunday and Monday if she promises to give him Monday, when they can see the soldiers or go anywhere she wants]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1898 Aug 7; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Bierce was unable to go to Oakland and wishes that he could run the world awhile, "My first official act would be to order you and Mamie to Los Gatos; my second, to go there myself."]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1898 Sep 15; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Thanks Hattie for the present of a cushion because it signified her return from her trip to a lake in the mountains and asks if he can visit her on Saturday afternoon]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1898 Nov 7; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Hopes that she is happier than in her last letter and asks individually about the health of her whole family]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Oakland, California, 1898 Nov 20; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Agrees to examine the manuscript of one of her friends if it is in typescript and legible and describes his new quarters in a house with six rooms, one of which he has reserved for her and her chaperon if she will visit]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1899 Feb 26; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Apologizes for his seeming inattention and answers her questions about the
    Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam
    ]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1899 May 4; ALS, 5 p., with envelope
    [Urges Hattie to come, rent a house, and visit several weeks in the area along with Belle and Florence, "Please say if you will come and thereby sweeten the fragrance of the flowers, intensify the gold of the sunshine and add a new music to the voices of my pet quails -one of which sits on my knee as I write and looks knowing as if he said: I can tell by your face whom you are writing to?"]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Waterman, California, 1899 Jun 25; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Expresses his disappointment that she did not come up to visit during her summer outing and determines to accustom himself to disappointment even to the point of allowing Harriet, Belle, and Florence to marry if they choose]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1899 Sep 10; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Asks her to again send the recipe for molasses candy for some of the ladies there want to make some and "as the purpose of my existence is to please the members of the sex which your virtues preserve from damnation I comply with the request"]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, Waterman, California, 1899 Oct 22; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Voices his concern over Louise's illness (malaria ?) and begs for news of her condition]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1899 Nov 24; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Asks for news of Louise and relates his plans to make a farewell visit to San Francisco before he returns to Washington, D.C. to live]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Wright's, California, to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1899 Nov 27; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Thanks Hattie for her good news about Louise and the invitation to Thanksgiving dinner which he must decline in the chaos of preparing to leave for Washington, D.C. but promises to try to see them all before he leaves]
  - Ambrose Bierce, The Lick House, to Harriet Hershberg, [ San Francisco, California], [1899 Dec ?]; ALS, 1 p., with envelope
    [Tells Hattie that he is to leave today and asks if she can keep herself and Louise and Belle at home long enough to see him before he leaves at 5 p.m.]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1900 Jan 21; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Tells her that "it is not worthwhile to love you anymore, for I shall never see you again" even if she should visit Pittsburgh because the coal smoke from the railway engines makes him very ill and there is little else in Pittsburgh. ]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1900 Mar 24; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Asks about the family and when she will be able to visit her sister Nettie in Pittsburgh and him in Washington]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1900 May 12; ALS, 4 p., with envelope
    [Declares that if he shall ever see those whom he loves again he will have to do the traveling "to the imminent destruction of my lungs" and wishes her "as much happiness as I can make up my mind that you ought to have in my absence"]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, San Francisco, California, 1900 Aug 8; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Hopes to see her in Washington before she leaves on her trip to Europe with her sister Nettie and offers to show her the capital]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1900 Dec 1; ALS, 4 p., with envelope
    [Having just returned from an unpleasant fortnight in New York, Bierce hopes that Hattie will be able to visit him in Washington, although he would be willing to return to New York to see her]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1900 Dec 27; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Bierce looks forward to seeing Harriet in a few days and describes his Christmas Day activities]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1901 Feb 8; ALS, 3 p., with envelope
    [Assures her that he is not angry that she won't be coming to Washington because "I have lived long enough to learn that a woman's promise is merely the expression of a mood -and woman's moods do not last long."]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg), New York City, [1901 Feb 20]; ALS, 2 p., with envelope
    [He is glad that Hattie had a good time in Washington during her visit and that she is enjoying New York City as well but does not plan to see her in New York]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1901 June 10; ALS, 2 p., with envelope
    [Thanks her for her expression of sympathy and mentions that his daughter is visiting with him]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Washington, D.C., to Harriet Hershberg, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1901 Jul 10; TLS, 2 p., with envelope
    [Bierce writes that he hopes her reasons for staying in the East so long is due to having such a good time and not the matchmaking attempts of Sally and Nettie, and he also touts his typewriting ability "I have one great qualification: I can hold my tongue, though sometimes both hands are required to do the job"]
  - Ambrose Bierce, Aurora, West Virginia, to Harriet Hershberg, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1903 Sep 27; ALS, 3 p.
    [Having received her note about her impending marriage Bierce writes, "It is pleasant to know that you still live, though about to die -I mean marry and live in Philadelphia. I approve the marriage, but Philadelphia! -that is going too far" and asks for news of everyone]